Okay,
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ח. lamed chet. And
let me just adjust that a little down. Thank you. And we
pick up with מאי נינהו, mai ninhu, four lines down. And this
is now into the technical issues about an animal that is a
מסוכנת, mesukenet, moribund, as we said, which means that it collapses even
when you try to stand it up. It has to show some
signs of life during the act of שחיטה shechita in order to
prove to us that it hasn't died before we succeeded in shechting
it. And those signs of life are פרכוס, pirchus, different types of
jerking and so on. What constitutes a jerking? So שמואל Shmuel has
now articulated it in a very broad way, any type of movement
that is not המיתה עושה, hamisa oseh, any type of movement that
doesn't directly result or wouldn't normally directly result just from the death
itself. Okay, so now we're even if
it moos, or whatever it is, right?
Right, רב Rav had mentioned mooing as well, correct. Thank you. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask what exactly this
includes. So מאי נינהו דברים שהמיתה עושה? mai ninhu dvarim shehamisa osa?
What are the things that death does? Meaning that we would have
to exclude because essentially we'll sort of like say everything is included
unless things that we identify as things that happen as a result
of death. So that is, you know, that's a very way of
having a very broad large category. So let's identify now those things
that we have to exclude. Thank you. A little more piling up
those things over there. I forgot that that was your seat. Okay,
so what are the things that death does? So אמר רבנן לדידי
מפרשא לי מיניה דמר שמואל, amar Ravnan lidi deparshuli minei demar Shmuel,
for me it was explained, you know, based on שמואל's Shmuel position,
to explicate שמואל's Shmuel position. היתה ידה כפופה ופשטתה דבר שהמיתה עושה.
Haysa yada kepufa upashtata davar shehamisa osa.
If the hand was bent and it stuck it out, that would
be a natural result of death. That's implicit in the משנה, Mishnah,
because the משנה Mishnah says if it sticks it out and doesn't
retrieve it, it's not movement. But now the other half of the
line is פשוטה וכפפתה, peshuta vechafafta, if the hand was extended and
it bent it in, דברים שאין המיתה עושה, dvarim she'ein hamisa osa,
that's not a result of death, which sort of makes sense. Right?
You sort of imagine something dying, it's like going to spread out,
it's not going to pull itself in. But what do I know?
I'm not a pathologist. Anyway, so that doesn't have as a result
of death and therefore it would constitute legitimate movement. So the גמרא
Gemara says, מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what are you telling
us that I don't already know? תנינא, tenina, we taught in our
משנה: Mishnah: בהמה דקה, behema daka, a small animal, a goat or
a sheep, שפשטה ידה ולא החזירה, shepashta yada velo hechzira, that extended
its hand without pulling it back, פסולה, pesula, that is a problem
if it was a מסוכנת. mesukenet. That is not sufficient movement, שאין
אלא הוצאת הנפש. she'ein ela hotza'as hanefesh.
So that's just the leaving of the soul. That's not a movement
that shows life, it's a movement that comes with death. הא דהחזירה,
ha dehechzira, from that I can infer that if the hand was
outstretched and it pulled it back, כשרה, keshera, it is valid. גמרא
Gemara says, no, אם ממתניתין הוה אמינא, im hamasnisa hava amina, from
our משנה Mishnah I would have thought, and this is a very
reasonable read of our משנה: Mishnah: דוקא דכייפא ופשטה והדר כייפא. davka
dekaifa upashta vahadar kaifa.
It says if it stuck it out and didn't pull it back
it's no good. So what would I have thought would be good?
That it stuck it out and pulled it back, it did both
movements. That I could have inferred would have been good. אבל פשוטה
וכפפתה, aval peshuta vechafafta,
but if it was just stretched out and it pulled it in,
it was only one movement, but it was in the pulling in
direction, לא, lo, I might have thought that's not sufficient. I might
have thought it needed both directions. קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, that even
that one direction suffices. So stretching the hand out does not suffice,
pulling the hand in does. Okay. So מיתיבי, maysivei, the גמרא Gemara
says I'll ask you on the based on the earlier statement, not
on שמואל Shmuel per se, but somebody's earlier statement. רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yose omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says this is from a
תוספתא: Tosefta: היה רבי מאיר אומר, haya Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir used to say, גועה בשעת שחיטה אין זה פרכוס. go'eh
besha'as shechita ein ze pirchus.
If it just mooed during the time of שחיטה shechita that does
not suffice. Now remember רב Rav said that mooing was sufficient. רבי
אלעזר ברבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi
Elazar
berabbi Yose omer, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar the son of רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose says in the name of his father, in the name
of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, so he adds to what רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose said, or אפילו הטילה רעי, afillu hitila re'i,
even if it defecated, which is also an example of רב, Rav,
וכשכשה בזנבה, vekishkesa biznava, or it slapped its tail, אין זה פרכוס.
ein ze pirchus.
That does not count. So basically everything that רב Rav said counts,
this תוספתא Tosefta says does not count. Okay, now you know one
way of reconciling it, of course it's quite a bit surprising that
רב's Rav list is exactly the list of the תוספתא, Tosefta, but
with the opposite.
Was it אזנא? ozna? He had אזנא. ozna.
This was זנבא. znava. That's a good point. Okay, that's a good
point. He had אזנא, ozna, this was זנבא. znava. But anyway, one
could imagine that רב's Rav statement was exactly articulated to reject the
תוספתא, Tosefta, to say the תוספתא Tosefta adds all of these exclusions,
but I'm going to say these exclusions aren't in the משנה Mishnah
and that these cases suffice you could have just read רב Rav
*Rav* straight like that to clarify that the תוספתא Tosefta. *Tosefta* is
not what the פשט pshat *Pshat* of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* is.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try to reconcile so
let's take a look. Said the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this
קשיא גועה אגועה *Kashya goah a goah* קשיא רעי ארעי *kashya re'i
a re'i*. So the mooing is a contradiction with רב *Rav*'s statement
about mooing and the defecating with רב *Rav*'s statement of defecating. Michael
is correct it didn't ask about the flapping because one was the
ear and the other was the tail. גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says לא lo, קשיא *Lo kashya* those don't have to be
a contradiction הא דאבי קלא *Ha de-avi kala* הא דאמי קלא *ha
de-ami kala*. If it's a deep low sound or it's a light
sound a high sound. So if it's a deep and it's a
low and it's a strong sound that's a sound of life. If
it is a weak sound that is just an expressing of breath
the oxygen leaving its lungs at the time of death it is
not a sound of life. That is the mooing issue. רעי ארעי
נמי לא קשיא *Re'i
a re'i nami lo kashya* defecating and defecating is not a problem
כאן בשוטתת כאן במתרזת *Kan beshotetes כאן במתרזת Kan bemitarezet*. One case
is that it sort of drips out so that and that obviously
is just again sort of the bowels evacuating themselves not a sign
of life. The other is that it really sort of throws it
out meaning at a distance and that's a real sign of life
that's
not just the releasing of the bowel. It's interesting by the way
again I don't know
Seth you didn't do any pathology in your medical school? No Michael.
Oh you went to medical school? Oh psychiatry I didn't know that.
Oh I'm sorry. Okay anyway so
but okay anyway so I don't know whether a pathologist would say
about this but I do want to point out an interesting thing
here I'm reading this according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* but there's an
interesting thing here structurally right? Because when it said אבי קלא *Avi
kala* and אמי קלא *ami kala* the low strong sound the first
of the pair was the sign of life אבי קלא *Avi kala*.
The next thing when it talks about the defecating it says שוטתת
*shotetes* and מתרזת *mitarezet* the second one is the sign of life
right? So it's a little interesting I mean I read it the
way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* did I wonder if somebody could read it
the other way because it's not parallel how it's structuring the pairs.
But in the first case first it gives you the sign of
life against the just natural occurrence during death and in the second
pair it reverses the order at least the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
explains this.
I know we've talked about animals is there any application to signs
of death?
Well this is not a sign of death this is more
at what stage did it die to determine like whether the שחיטה
Shechita *shechita* was good. But yeah the more relevant question is all
those discussions about נבילה *neveila* and first is נבילה *neveila* by an
animal to define it as dead or not the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is quite contradictory about that question and then the question is right
can you apply it to humans? So when we are actually trying
to define when an animal is dead then there is some question
about how relevant that is for humans. But here we're not trying
to define when it died we're trying to actually define can you
sort of like the opposite we suspect it might have died because
it was מסוכנת mesukenes, *mesukenet* do we have proof that it was
still alive at the time of
שחיטה Shechita *shechita*? Okay so alright so let's take a look. אמר
רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda, *Amar Rav Chisda* פרכוס שאמרו pirchus she'amru,
*Pirchush she-amru* when they spoke about these movements whatever the movements are
here becomes an important question when was that movement exhibited? Now again
remember that what we're trying to prove is that when you got
around to shechting the second סימן siman *siman* when you finished the
שחיטה Shechita *shechita* it was still alive. So it was the שחיטה
Shechita *shechita* the final act of שחיטה Shechita *shechita* that killed it
or whether שחיטה Shechita. *shechita* has to kill or not it doesn't
matter but anyway it was the act of שחיטה Shechita. *shechita* was
done on a live animal it didn't die beforehand. So therefore you
might think that it had to exhibit the sign of life before
the שחיטה Shechita *shechita* is complete. Of course on the other hand
that might not suffice if it exhibited towards the beginning of the
process maybe by the time you got to the end of the
שחיטה Shechita *shechita* it already died. Okay on the other hand if
you demand that it has to exhibit the sign of life after
the שחיטה Shechita *shechita* maybe you're asking for too much once you've
done the שחיטה Shechita, *shechita* it doesn't have to be alive anymore.
So when are you what is going to suffice and when are
you going to demand that sign of life? Later should certainly prove
it but it might be demanding too much. Earlier you could say
if it has the sign of life at the middle of the
שחיטה Shechita *shechita* we can assume it will still have been alive
by the time the שחיטה Shechita *shechita* is over. So it has
to be exactly at the second but that's also a little unrealistic
to try to get it pinpointed exactly at that time. So let's
see with that in mind we're going to see three opinions in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* when it has to exhibit this sign of
life. So let's take a look.
Interesting yes they're actually very kind of scientific in this case in
terms of as always does try and establish exact definitions boundaries and
so on although one could posit that maybe that's not really the
case
I
mean it's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s understanding of those issues right
and that is Yeah, but the, you know, a more, I don't
know, a different approach is for example what there is again referring
to the human death. I think רב Soloveitchik posited at one point
that it's a process as opposed to a definition. So it's interesting
as this גמרא Gemara, is, you know, takes this kind of scientific
approach.
Right, right. I mean, but you're right and in another way it's
just doing what it normally does in any area of הלכה, Halacha,
which is okay, what are the exact parameters? But again, then that's
back to Seth's point. It's not here trying to define death. It's
just trying to define
proof that it's still alive. Yeah, but often that there is, there
is a point at which, you know, the animal dies and separates
life and death.
Well, right. I mean look, you know,
even רב Aaron Soloveitchik who says it's a process, you know, I
never understood the point, well, I guess I did understand it, but
even if you say it's a process, at one point the process
is over. Person really is dead, animal really is dead.
Right, but you don't know, you can't define exactly when
that, when that occurs.
There is no clear line that divides life from death. Aha, that's
the point, and clearly the assumption here is that there is because
you have the animal thrashing.
Well, no, because you could say, well, whether that's true or not,
no, because you don't have to say שחיטה Shechita. is death, you
just have to say שחיטה Shechita. is שחיטה Shechita. and you have
to do שחיטה Shechita. while it's still alive. So
I never understood what is exactly, okay, this is a digression, but
this idea that it's a process, does that mean that there are
stages that הלכה Halacha recognizes as quasi-alive and quasi-dead, that there's meaningful
middle stages, or does it mean no, no, no, you're either definitely
alive or definitely dead, it's sort of like the בין השמשות, bein
hashmashos, we just can't pinpoint it? Was that exactly the בין השמשות
bein hashmashos debate? Is בין השמשות bein hashmashos that there is a
line between day and night, it's just we don't know where to
point it, or is it that there actually is a period called
an interim period which is neither day nor night?
And that's what I was wondering about the signs in the animal
and the implications for humans.
I see, I see.
But anyway, again here it's not trying to pinpoint a moment of
death, it's just trying to assert that it was still alive when
the שחיטה Shechita? occurred. Okay, so let's take a look. So, אמר
רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, פרכוס pirchus שאמרו,
this thrashing or movement, בסוף שחיטה, besof shechita, has to be at
the end of the שחיטה. shechita? So מאי בסוף שחיטה? mai besof
shechita? Interestingly the גמרא Gemara now decides to reframe his statement, or
רש"י Rashi actually says that רב חסדא Rav Chisda himself is saying
this because it's a little strange the גמרא Gemara would, that I
heard a tradition, whoever I heard it from, I heard a ruling
of בסוף שחיטה, besof shechita, but I am going to understand it
in the following way. That what does בסוף שחיטה besof shechita mean?
באמצע שחיטה. be'emtza shechita. It really means not at the end, it
just means not at the beginning,
לאפוקי תחלת שחיטה דלא, l'afokei techilas shechita d'lo, to exclude the beginning.
If it has this sign at the very beginning of the act,
that doesn't prove anything yet, it's just begun. It has to still
show this sign of life during the act. Okay, and during, you
know, you could say the, that's at least maybe as close as
you can get till the second of the final finality of the
שחיטה. shechita, But at the very end, you know, that already that's
too high of a demand. Once the שחיטה shechita is dead, is
done, to still demand that you show a sign of life. So
let's take a look. There's going to be basically all three opinions,
beginning, middle, and end. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר amar
רב חסדא, מנא אמינא לה, mina amina la, where do I get
this idea that it means the middle? דתנן, detnan, we taught in
our משנה, Mishnah. ובהמה דקה שפשטה ידה ולא החזירה פסולה, ve-heima daka
she-pashat yada v'lo hechizira pesula, if it stuck out a hand and
did not pull it back, it's invalid. אימת, eimas, so when are
we talking about that this sign of life does not suffice?
אילימא בסוף שחיטה, ileyma besof shechita, at the end? So
כל היכא דתיהי ותיזיל? kohl haycha teichi v'teizei? You expect it to
live? How long do you expect it to live?
Meaning you know, even a healthy animal when it's just slaughtered.
Exactly! So how can you demand a sign of life, you know,
or the opposite, it's funny that it sort of makes this commentary
on the statement of פסולה, pesula, but it basically is saying, wait
a minute, meaning right, it's basically saying that if even this sign,
here's a sign that's not sufficiency for you, because the hand spreading
out. How could that not be sufficient if it was after the
שחיטה shechita was done? If it was after the שחיטה shechita was
done, even that sign should suffice, because it's, you know, if it
still has some life after שחיטה, shechita. that should be sufficient. Of
course it's a little funny question because if we said before that
that is just a normal way in which the, you know, in
which a movement that comes with death, what exactly does that prove?
But you know, another way of reframing it is not focusing on
what's פסול, pasul, but just saying look, how can you demand a
sign of life, a high criteria for a sign of life after
the שחיטה's shechita. done? What do you expect after the שחיטה's shechita,
done? It's already שחט. shechted. כל היכא דתיהי ותיזיל? kohl haycha teichi
v'teizei? You want it to live? How long do you want it
to live? אלא באמצע שחיטה, ella be'emtza shechita, it must be the
middle of the שחיטה. shechita. So really it's not so much a
textual proof, it's really almost just like a logical statement, you know.
Rather, you know, logically it's asking too much to show a sign
of life after שחיטה. shechita, It most makes sense during שחיטה. shechita.
Fine. אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said no,
לעולם בסוף שחיטה, l'olam besof shechita, I can demand it at the
end of שחיטה. shechita, So how can you demand it at the
end of שחיטה? shechita, By then it's already שחט. shechted. Because ושני
אומר, u'shani omer, I'll say, כל... kohl... So how can you demand
it at the end of שחיטה? shechita. By then it's already שחט'ד.
shechted. Because כשאני אומר, keshe ani omer, I'll say, כל שאינו עושה
כן בסוף שחיטה, kol she-eino oseh kein besof shechita, if it can't
do this after the שחיטה, shechita בידוע שנשמתו נטלה הימנו קודם לכן,
be-yadu-a she-nishmato nitla hemenu kodem lakhen, it is known or I have
to assume that it died earlier. So meaning basically what רבא Rava
is saying is, look, you're right. It doesn't have to be alive
after שחיטה shechita, is done. But if I don't see a sign
of life after שחיטה shechita. is done, I can't assume it was
alive when the שחיטה shechita, was complete. So technically you're right. What
we only we don't have to prove life after שחיטה. shechita, We
only have to prove life at the moment of שחיטה. shechita, But
if I don't have this sign after שחיטה, shechita I cannot therefore
assume that it was still alive during שחיטה.
shechita But regular animal you can assume?
Right, so that's why I rephrased it and said assume because the
way it's stated by רבא Rava is too strong, I know it
wasn't alive. You know, you have to say, I know that if
it was a מסוכנת, mesukenes it wasn't alive and so on. Right,
but it basically means in a case of a מסוכנת mesukenet where
I need to prove life at the moment of שחיטה, shechita. in
order to prove that, I'm going to need to see life after
שחיטה. shechita. Okay, during's not gonna suffice. Alright, so yeah, you're right,
what we're only trying to prove is during is at the moment
of שחיטה, shechita but in order to prove that, I need to
say something after שחיטה, shechita, see something after שחיטה. shechita Okay. קודם
לכן. Kodem lakhen. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
amar, פרכוס שאמרו בתחילת שחיטה. pirchus she-amru bi-tchilat shechita. He is very
lenient. He says as long as it can show this even in
the beginning of the process, that shows that it we can you
know that's a good enough evidence that it'll still be alive when
the שחיטה shechita completes. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak,
so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said, מנא אמינא
לה, mena amina lah, where'd I get this from? דתנן, De-tenan, we
turn to a משנה. Mishnah אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, השוחט
בלילה, ha-shochet ba-layla, ובמחר מצא כותלים מלאים דם, u-be-machar matza kotlim meleim
dam, you shechted at night and then you woke up in the
morning, you found the walls—we'll interpret what the walls mean in a
minute—filled with blood. כשרה, Keshera, שזינקה, she-zinka, it's kosher because I can
assume it squirted blood, obviously. וכמידת רבי אלעזר, U-ke-midat Rabbi Elazar, like
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that says squirting of blood is a sign
of life. ואמר שמואל, Ve-amar Shmuel, now שמואל Shmuel said, כותלי בית
השחיטה שנינו, kotlei beis ha-shechita shoninu, we didn't mean the walls in
the room, we meant the walls of the place of שחיטה, shechita.
meaning the actual like cut in the neck. That was filled with
blood. I'll go back in a minute to say why it's important
to introduce that here. So he says, look, let's—so you שחט'ד, shechted,
you walked away, you came back the next morning, you found that
there was blood all over the place of שחיטה. shechita Now, אי
אמרת בשלמא בתחילת שחיטה, ei amart bishlama bi-tchilat shechita, if you say
any sign of life is or movement or whatever works even at
the beginning of שחיטה, shechitah שפיר, shapir, then it's good. Then I
don't have to care, when did this squirting of blood occur? Did
it occur at the beginning, the middle, or the end? It doesn't
matter, even if it occurred at the beginning, that suffices. אלא אי
אמרת בסוף שחיטה, Ella ei amart be-sof shechita, but if you said
that you needed only the sign of life at the end, middle
or end, beginning is not good, so if that's true, ליחוש דילמא
בתחילת שחיטה זינקה, leichush dilma bi-tchilat shechita zinka, how can I just
if I see the blood, yes I know it squirted, but this
is a very good point. If according to what matters when that
when that action happened, right? When that movement happened, so how can
I just because it did happen, it's not sufficient. I need to
know it happened only at the middle or at the end. So
yes I know it squirted, but who cares? Maybe it only squirted
in the middle, maybe it only squirted in the end. The fact
that I say from the fact that it squirted it's okay, it
shows that it doesn't matter when it squirts, even if the movement
occurs in the beginning, you're okay. So the so that's a very
nice proof. So let's see what the גמרא'ס Gemara's response is. גמרא
Gemara says, ודילמא שאני זינוק דעדיף. ve-dilma shani zinuk de-adif.
Okay, maybe squirting is a better sign. So squirting, you've proven squirting.
Squirting we don't have to know when it occurred, that could occur
even in the beginning. But other signs of life maybe have to
occur later on. Now before we go on, I want to say,
why'd the גמרא Gemara introduce the idea that the place you saw
the blood was the place of the cut and not the walls
of the room?
I don't think it says is it משמע mashma from the לשון
lashon of the משנה Mishnah, that it means the walls of the
room, because מלאים דם, meleim dam, I mean like you need like
what, you have this whole wall full of blood?
Well yes, you might actually have well, no, it just means you
know there's serious blood on the wall. Actually that I mean, you
could have argued the opposite. I could have said if all you
need is the בית השחיטה, beis ha-shechita, what type of sign of
life is it that blood comes out? You know, any any animal
blood will come out. But if you actually see the blood splattered
on the wall, that's a different story. Anyway, רש"י Rashi says the
reason it was introduced here, whatever motivates that interpretation of the משנה,
Mishna, the reason it's introduced here, רש"י Rashi says, is because if
it literally meant the walls of the room, then you could have
said that's evidence that it occurred you know at the end. Because
according to the גמרא Gemara just—according to the גמרא, Gemara I mean
this is I'm sure just at the שוחט, shochet, you'll have the
answer—but what happens is as soon as you שחט shecht an animal,
the blood starts dripping and then after a few whatever seconds or
milliseconds of dripping, then it squirts. So it doesn't start by squirting.
So if so if it literally meant the walls of the room,
רש"י Rashi said, then it wouldn't have been a good proof. Because
then you would have said that yes, we can assume it wasn't
the beginning. At the beginning, it never would have squirted all the
way to the all the way to hit the walls. But since
שמואל Shmuel says we're not talking about the walls of the room,
we're just talking about filling the place of the cut, you know,
with blood, so then you really don't know, maybe that occurs at
the beginning. So you see that really it is not it doesn't
matter when this thing occurs. Now again, I have to say that
it is completely bizarre that this counts at all because, right? How
dead do you want an animal to be that no blood comes
out? So that's mean... But the point is that it's still funny
that this is a סימן *siman* because, you know, again, I'm not
a שוחט *shochet*, but you would imagine that even if an animal
is pretty sickly and about to die, that blood is going to
come out and fill the בית השחיטה *beis ha-shechita*. So anyway, but
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, okay, you've proven that that can
be at the beginning because we rule that way without knowing, but
maybe it's because the blood is a stronger sign, which seems very
strange. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to say, well, is
that really true? Let's take a look. ומי עדיף *u-mi adif*? Can
you really say that the squirting of blood is a stronger sign
than the other thing? והתנן *ve-hatnan*, in our משנה Mishna. *Mishna* we
taught, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר דיה אם זינקה *Rabbi Eliezer omer
daya im zinka*. It is sufficient if it squirts blood. So you
see that squirting blood is a weaker sign than the other thing.
Why is it a weaker sign? Because it suffices that it squirts
blood. So squirting blood is not as strong of a sign as
the other thing. You don't need it to move the arm and
the foot. Squirting blood suffices. That's how רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer* is introduced, so obviously it's a weaker sign.
If it were a stronger sign, it would have said קל וחומר
kal v'chomer אם זינקה *kal va-chomer im zinka*.
No, he would say עד שיזנק *ad
she-yizanek* or דיה *daya*. Suffices means that that's even less of a
threshold. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, that's true, but he's
responding to רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* that required both the hand and
the foot. So קל מדרבן גמליאל *kal mi-Rabban Gamliel*, he's less demanding
than רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* that required the hand and the foot,
ואדיף מדרבנן *va-adif mi-Rabbanan*, but maybe it's a stronger sign than the
רבנן *Rabbanan* who say hand or foot. And we're talking within the
רבנן *Rabbanan*. So when we talk about just hand or foot, maybe
that has to be at the end, but maybe squirting is a
stronger sign and that could be even at the beginning.
Maybe squirting is related to the beating of the heart. Aha.
So it won't be able to pump it far. See, that's fine,
but that's if you say that it has to hit something at
a distance. It has to actually squirt out, right? But if it's
קטלי בית השחיטה *ketale beis ha-shechita*, right? So even unless you assume
that no, if it just dribbles out, if it's not really coming
out with any strength, it's not going to fill the
entire, but I don't know. I mean, aren't there like blood vessels
like on both sides, right? There's like the carotid artery on both
sides. So even if it was just dribbling out, again, I don't
know. Yeah. Presumably not. Presumably it needs some strong pumping to get
it to fill the בית השחיטה *beis ha-shechita* with blood. Okay. Yeah,
it seems to be. So anyway, so now we're trying to
figure out that's by birds, I assume that
there's a real difference. בית השחיטה *Beis ha-shechita* is smaller by birds,
but birds have small hearts.
So none of this would apply to a bird? I don't know,
a bird is מסופק *mesupak*.
So all of these discussions are in the context of, you know,
cows or בהמה דקה *behema daka*. I don't know whether it would
translate or whether it would translate to a bird. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רבינא *amar Ravina*, so רבינא *Ravina* said,
אמר לי סמא בר חלקייא *amar li Sama bar Chilkiya*, so סמא
בר חלקייא *Sama bar Chilkiya* said, interesting name, הכי קאמר אבוה דבר
אבוורם *hachi ka-amar avuha de-var Avuvram*, that's the father of the son
of אבוורם *Avuvram*. So guess what his name
was? אבוורם *Avuvram*! So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says the reason he's called
the father of the son of אבוורם *Avuvram* is because his son
was the more prestigious person. But of course then why are they
calling him the son of אבוורם *Avuvram*? Why don't they call him
by his name? So I don't know. Anyway, so here is the
retort to that. We're trying to argue that yes, you prove that
squirting can come at the beginning, but maybe it's a stronger sign.
So let's take a look if you can really say that squirting
is a stronger sign. ומדרבנן מי אדיף *u-mi-Rabbanan mi adif*? Is it
really a stronger sign than the רבנן *Rabbanan*? Is רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* really demanding more than the רבנן *Rabbanan*? והתנן *ve-hatnan*,
our משנה Mishna *Mishna*, after רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says
his idea of squirting, remember our משנה *Mishna* first רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel* said hand and foot, then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
said squirting, and then the רבנן *Rabbanan* said hand or foot. So
when the רבנן *Rabbanan* said hand or foot, they said וחכמים אומרים
עד שתפרכס או ביד B'yad, או ברגל *ve-Chachamim omrim ad she-tefarches o
be-yad o be-regel*, until it's not a good sign until it moves
with the hand or the foot. So the word until means that
they're demanding more. So רבנן אהיי קיימי *Rabbanan ahay kaymi*? Who are
they responding to? אילימא דרבן גמליאל *ileima de-Rabban Gamliel*, רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel* that says you need a hand and foot. So the right
response to say hand and foot is not until it's hand or
foot. Until means what you said wasn't enough, you have to get
to what I'm saying, you have to get to my level. So
you don't say until hand or foot if they're responding to somebody
that says hand and foot. So if they're responding to רבן גמליאל
*Rabban Gamliel*, כיון שפרכסה מיבעי ליה *keivan she-perchasa mibei lei*, they should
have said as soon as it does the hand or foot it's
enough, you don't need both. אלא פשיטא אדרבי אליעזר *ella peshita ad-Rabbi
Eliezer*, they're responding to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי Rabbi,
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says squirting and the רבנן *Rabbanan* say no, squirting
isn't enough, you need hand or foot until you get one of
those you're not good. So you see that the רבנן *Rabbanan* position
is a stronger sign than the squirting. ואי אדיף *ve-i adif*, and
if squirting is a stronger
sign... strong evidence. If squirting when we don't know when it occurred,
right, it hit at night, you came back the next morning, and
if that's sufficient at any time, so then the other movements which
based on this read of the משנה are even stronger evidence of
life, certainly should be sufficient at any time. And it's interesting that
the גמרא Gemara doesn't have an answer to that. But now we
have a position articulated middle and a position articulated beginning, so we're
left with the third possibility which is end. So let's take a
look. רבא Rava אמר רבא Amar Rava, says, פרכוס ששאמרו בסוף שחיטה.
pirchus she'amru besof shechita. The פרכוס
has to be at the end. In order for it to be
evidence of life, although it doesn't have to be alive after שחיטה,
shechitah but to know it was alive at שחיטה, shechitah you need
to see this סימן at the end. Now by the way, I
should point out that notice of course what a thing the גמרא
Gemara could have easily introduced in all this debate was
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף yeshna lishchita mitechila ve'ad sof or אינה
לשחיטה אלא לבסוף, eina lishchita ela levasof, right? Is שחיטה shechitah at
the end, is it the whole process and so on. But for
a good reason the גמרא Gemara didn't introduce that, because that's all
a halachic question. You know, you know, do we define שחיטה shechitah,
from the beginning, define it at the end and so on. This
is a real world question. Was it alive throughout the שחיטה. So
therefore the question of formally when do I say the whole process
does it's at the beginning, at the end etc, that's not being
introduced although here you have a question beginning, middle or end, it's
not connected to another debate of beginning, middle or end of the
process of defining שחיטה. Because this is a simple real world question
of can we assume it was alive when the שחיטה finished. Okay,
so רבא Rava says it has to be at the end. You
have to see it at the end. אמר רבא מנא אמינא לה.
amar Rava mna amina la. Where do I get this from? תניא
tanya we taught in the ברייתא. braita. שור או כשב. shor o
kesev.
Okay, this is moving to a different field and the proof here
is going to be a little bit strange, which I really don't
understand. But anyway, right, the תורה Torah says שור או כשב או
עז כי יולד והיה שבעת ימים תחת אמו ומיום השמיני והלאה ירצה.
shor o kesev o ez ki yivaled vehaya shivat yamim tachat imo
umiyom hashmini vahal'a yeiratze. So an ox or a sheep or a
goat that is born, is he has to be with its mother
for seven days and only on the eighth day can be brought
as a קרבן. korban. So now we're going to learn a lot
of things from here about what constitutes a good קרבן korban or
not. So let's take a look. שור או כשב, shor o kesev,
so first פרט לכלאים. perat lekhilayim. It has to be either an
ox or a sheep or a goat, no hybrid. No type of
a crossbreed between a sheep and a goat. I don't even know
if you can do that. But anyway, no crossbreeds. או עז, o
ez, or a goat, פרט לנדמה. perat lenidme. So the emphasis again
by separating these out individually means that it has to be like
very clearly one
species. A, the genotype, meaning in reality it has to just be
one species. And number two, the phenotype, it can't even look like
a different species than it actually is. Okay, it can't be appear
to be some type of a
crossbreed or of a different species. Okay, כי
יולד ki yivaled when it is born, פרט ליוצא דופן perat leyotzei
dofen excludes Cesarean birth. Okay, that now is considered not to be
born, or תוספות Tosafot says that maybe it's a גזירה שוה gezeira
shava from another place where it talks about a firstborn or describes
it as פטר רחם, peter rechem, you know, breaching, you know, coming,
you know, opening the womb, which therefore means vaginal birth and not
Cesarean. Or sometimes the גמרא makes the דרשה drasha for example אשה
כי תזריע וילדה זכר isha ki tazria veyaleda zachar that this is
about טומאת יולדת tumat yoledet right when a woman or also by
the way it's the idea that a ברית מילה bris mila on
the eighth day overrides שבת Shabbat is only by a vaginal birth
not by a Cesarean birth. And the גמרא learns that from the
fact that it says אשה כי תזריע וילדה זכר עד שיולדה ממקום
שמזרעת isha ki tazria veyaleda zachar ad sheyoleda mimakom shemazra'at until the
birth comes from the same place of the seed, you know, where
the seed enters and exits meaning it's a vaginal birth. So the
גמרא sometimes excludes Cesarean section either from כי תזריע ki tazria or
by the בכור פטר רחם, bechor peter rechem, right, which is opening
of the womb, which isn't that what Cesarean section is, but no
it means sort of the normal opening of the womb coming through
the cervix. Here it just excludes it from the phrase כי יולד
ki yivaled that's not like birth. But תוספות Tosafot says it's based
on connecting it to those other פסוקים. pesukim. Of course you know
we all I assume remember our Shakespeare, right, what is it,
no man not of a woman born?
No man not of a woman born from Macbeth. Who was that,
Banquo? Not Banquo.
Who was it,
who was it, Macduff?
No, I don't remember. Anyway, right, that he will only be his...
so anyway which was somebody that was born through Cesarean section. So
anyway, so you see it is possible to call it not real
birth. Okay, anyway, פרט ליוצא דופן perat leyotzei dofen excludes Cesarean section.
שבעת ימים shivat yamim seven days, פרט למחוסר זמן. perat limchusar zman.
Now not just פרט, perat, that's פשט of the פסוק. pasuk. Anything
less than seven, less than eight days old cannot be brought as
a קרבן. korban. That's really... is it like יום יום,
yom yom, eight to eight, does that...
oh that's a good question. Yeah, I forget the answer to that.
Okay. Okay, תחת אמו, tachas imo, it has to be under its
mother. Now we're going to get closer to what's relevant to us.
פרט ליתום. prat l'yasom. תחת אמו קיימת, tachas imo kayemes, right?
רש"י Rashi says right, so- right, that's just under- mother dies before
the- well, that's
what- that's the next line.
So that's what we're about to talk about.
Okay, פרט ליתום, prat l'yasom, to exclude the case of an orphan.
Now, meaning even if it's eight days old, if it was never-
if it never had a mother, then it is now- then it
is now... before those eight days or just...
Yeah, so רש"י Rashi says here,
we assume that means never had a mother. רש"י Rashi said why
do we read it that way? Why don't we read it that
it means that it needs to have a mother for all seven
days? The mother has to be alive the whole seven days. That's
what it sounds like, שבעת ימים תחת אמו. shivat yamim tachas imo.
So רש"י Rashi quotes a very long רש"י Rashi here, you know,
the מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, the ספרא, Sifra, that- that learns out
that it does not- it's not- should not be read to mean
that. To mean that it has to have the mother for all
seven days and just should be read in the more narrow way
that it needs to have had a mother
at least for
a second in its life. So at least when it was born,
it had to have a mother. Not a father. Meaning that- I
mean, obviously everything has a father, everything has to biologically... No, but
I mean the father doesn't have to be alive, correct. So the
mother of this sheep or cow or whatever had to be alive
at least for a second. At least had to have a mother
for one second. Again, רש"י Rashi shows based on מדרשי הלכה midrashei
halacha why we're not reading it to say all seven days. So
we're going to focus on this scenario that it died, at what
moment did it die, you know, at the moment of birth, right
after birth, right before birth, the mother, in order to, you know,
to be relevant for this פסוק. pasuk. So let's take a look.
האי יתום, hai yasom, this orphan, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the
case? אילימא דיילידתה אמה והדר מתה, eileima d'yalidta imeh v'hadar mesa, first-
first the mother gave birth to it and then the mother died,
so לעולם חייה וחייה אזלה? l'olam pachi pichizel? Do you want the
mother to live forever? No, no, it exists. I understand. But anyway,
the point is we're assuming that it only- the mother- it only
has to have a mother for one second. So obviously the mother
didn't die after it was born, then it would have been okay.
אלא דמתה בהדי ילידתה. ela d'mesa bahadi yelidta. So obviously we mean
that the mother died and then it had the child and the
cow was expelled from the womb- expelled? Really? Expelled somehow? Well, let's
take a look. Okay, so the גמרא's going to say, no, מכיוון
דאפקי נפקא. mikeivan d'afki nafka. That would not have been a vaginal
birth, that would have had to have been a cesarean section. It
assumes that if the mother died first, then you'd have to cut
the womb open. So when are you going to get this born
that the mother will have died? It can't have been died before,
it can't have been died- then it won't be born vaginally. It
can't have been died after
because then it would have satisfied. So it must have been it
died at the moment, okay, at the moment of birth is also
the moment of death. אלא פשיטא זה פירש למיתה וזה פירש לחיים.
ela pshita zeh peireish l'misa v'zeh peireish l'chayim. This one went to
life and this one went to death. So at the moment of
halachic birth, let's say, whatever that is, the crowning of the head
or ראשו או רובו rosho o rubo or whatever, there was also
the same second that it died. So it was alive enough to-
to birth it, but it did not- it would- it did not
remain alive after, you know, the very second that the animal was
born, it also died. Okay, so now that's pretty precise. And- and
תוספות Tosafot raises the whole question about what about אי אפשר לצמצם?
i efshar l'tzamtzem? How are you ever supposed to know that? But
all right. So I don't know. He says, if you look at
the little תוספות, Tosafot, אלא זה פירש למיתה וזה פירש לחיים, ela
zeh peireish l'misa v'zeh peireish l'chayim, he says אין להוכיח מכאן דאפילו
בידי שמים אי אפשר לצמצם. ein l'hochiyach mikan d'afillu b'yedei shamayim i
efshar l'tzamtzem. You can't prove from here that even things
that are natural you can know the exact, you know, precise moment.
דקרא איכא למימר דאיצטריך אם יבא אליהו ויאמר שבצמצום נעשה. dikra ika
l'meimar d'itztarich im yavo Eliyahu v'yomar sheb'tzimtzum na'aseh. Okay, so you're right.
Maybe the פסוק pasuk is talking about a hypothetical that we will
never know, or maybe once hypothetically it's a problem, whenever we have
a doubt, we have to be strict, okay? But- but at least
we want to know what is the case the פסוק pasuk is
excluding. I'm sorry, is it- the פסוק pasuk is talking about what
happens- I don't know. The פסוק pasuk is talking when it happened
exactly at the same second, it's not valid as a קרבן, korban,
which means translated for us, even if we don't know that exact
second, if there's reason to think it might have occurred at that
exact second, then we can't bring it. Okay, so you don't have
to know that it exactly occurred, but that has to be the
case that the תורה Torah is talking about. Okay, anyway, so now
back to us. אי אמרת בשלמא בעינן חיותא בסוף לידה, ei amart
b'shlama ba'inan chiyusa b'sof leida, if you say that you need it
to be alive at the end of the birth, you know, היינו
דאיצטריך קרא למיעוטה, hainu d'itztarich kra l'miyutei, then you understand the scenario,
that an animal can be alive until the- through the- through the
second of birth and then the פסוק pasuk says even when that
occurs that it dies at the very last second, then it's going
to be invalid. אלא אי אמרת לא בעינן חיותא בסוף לידה, ela
ei amart lo ba'inan chiyusa b'sof leida, if you could say that
an animal might succeed in finishing birthing after it already has expired,
למה לי? lamo li? Why again, why- I'm sorry, I might have
said that wrong, one minute. Hold on a minute. Now, I'm sorry,
I mentioned some of the criteria. If it's saying that, that even,
that— I'm sorry— let me do this head, אלא אימא דלא בעינא
חיותא בסוף לידה, Ela eima d'lo baina chayuta b'sof leida, but if
the Torah is not demanding here that it be alive at the
end, it's only demanding that it be alive sometime, sometime in the
middle, but it doesn't have to be alive at the end, so
למה לי, lama li, why do you need to say this verse
of explaining an orphan? מחייו אולי נפקא, mechayav ulay nafka, you can
exclude it from again the issue of נפקא ברת, nafka brat, meaning
what? This is very bizarre and I have to tell you רש"י
Rashi also recognizes the problem and doesn't really answer. The point is
like this, he's saying, look, if you're going to— if—
if all the Torah is doing here is excluding a case where
it was alive earlier in the stage and then died before birth,
if that was all the Torah is excluding, that when it died
during the birth process before the birth had completed, right, then it
says then I don't need this פסוק pasuk about orphan, because then
if that's true that it died before the birth had completed, it
would be a case of a יוצא דופן, yotzei dofen, I'd have
to do a cesarean section anyway. So clearly what the Torah is
talking about, it's really repeating what it said before, it's not that
it died earlier in the process, it's that it died towards the
end. Okay, now that's all very lovely. What does that have to
do with a case of a מסוכנת and when it has to
show the sign of life? So רש"י says, oh, well since we
see in one place the Torah is focusing on it being alive
at the end, at the end of what, end of process of
birth, not a process of שחיטה, so therefore when I need a
sign of life in a process of שחיטה because I'm afraid it
died earlier, I'm going to want to see that sign of life
at the end. It makes absolutely no sense. One thing has nothing
to do with the other, right?
I mean— well, I
understand, I'm just saying I don't understand it. If you want to
look at רש"י because I don't have any decent explanation of this
גמרא, so take a look at רש"י
where the line that starts with there's a little ז zayin in
half brackets. It starts with the word הוי ליה יוצא דופן. havlei
yotzei dofen. It's about eight lines before the משנה, so רש"י says
אלא שמע מינה, ela shma mina, you see from this, כל מילתא
דבעו בה רבנן חיותא, kol milta d'bau bah rabbanan chayuta, interesting phrase,
whenever there's a concern of it still being alive, בעינן שתהא חיות
בגמר דיליה, beinan shetihei chayut b'gmar diley, it has to come at
the end of the process. Again, what a bizarre abstraction and analogy.
In one case, we want to talk about that this animal was
born vaginally but it's an orphan, so we talk about the mother
being alive at the end through the end of birth. Therefore, in
another case when we're concerned about an animal that might have died
before שחיטה and we need a sign of life, we're going to
need that sign of life to be at the end of the
process and at the end of the שחיטה. Okay, very strange, תוספות
Tosafot does not help either, some very, very sort of weak analogy
to show that it's the end. But whatever the case is, רבא
Rava says we need the sign of life at the end. Okay,
now we're going to try to wrap this up. אמר רבא, Rava
so says רבא, Rava, הלכתא, hilchata, the הלכה halacha is, כי האי
מתניתין, ki hai matnitin, like the following משנה. Now we're no longer
about beginning, middle, end. Beginning, middle, end we had three opinions.
I knew you were going to ask that, I don't know. You'll
take a look. Look at the רמב"ם Rambam here, is there a
hint here which way we said? Yeah, well the little letter here
is by רבא's Rava position of the סוף, sof, which is the
weakest in terms of all of the evidence, right, but nevertheless it's
the most מחמיר, machmir, right, you're not going to- you're going to
have to suspect that the animal died unless you can prove a
sign of life even at the end of the process. So that's
the strictest position, that's רבא, Rava, at least just looking here it
seems like that's the way we rule. So you have the different
positions beginning, middle, and end, but now we're going to have one
final discussion about what constitutes movement. So let's take a look.
Where are we?
Okay, אמר רבא הלכתא כי האי מתניתין, Amar Rava hilchata ki hai
matnitin, and הלכה halacha is like the following ברייתא braita which is
a תוספתא. בהמה דקה שפשטה ידה ולא החזירה פסולה. Behema daka she-pashta
yada v'lo hechzira psula.
If it's a small animal, sheep or goat, and it stuck out
the hand and didn't pull it back, invalid. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh
devarim amurim, when is that true? ביד, if we're talking about the
forearm. אבל ברגל, Aval b'regel, if it's the hind leg, בין פשטה
ולא כפפה בין כפפה ולא פשטה כשירה, bein pashta v'lo kfafa bein
kfafa v'lo pashta ksheira, whether it stuck it out without pulling it
in or pulled it in without sticking it out, that's okay. Either
movement in the hind leg suffices. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim,
and when is this true all together that sticking out the front
leg is no
good? בדקה, B'daka, by a small animal like a sheep or a
goat. אבל בגסה, Aval b'gasa, by a large animal, a cow, אבל
בגסה,
aval
b'gasa, where am I? בין ביד בין ברגל בין פשטה ולא כפפה
בין כפפה ולא פשטה כשירה, bein b'yad bein b'regel bein pashta v'lo
kfafa bein kfafa v'lo pashta ksheira, whether it's the front leg or
the hind leg, whether out or not in or in and not
out, it's valid. Okay, so everything is valid by a cow. The
only thing we are excluding when it's one movement is a small
animal, front leg, going out and not going in. That's the one
case we're excluding. ובעוף, U'v'of, ah, here we go, here's the bird
case, and when it comes to the bird. Birds, apparently we can
identify מסוכנת *mesukenet* by birds although
we weren't told how. But if you identify as מסוכנת *mesukenet*, here's
what you need as a sign of movement. אפילו לא רפרף אלא
גפו *Afilu lo rifref ela gapo*, even if it didn't ruffle, like
that translation, רפרף *rifref*, only its wing, ולא כשכש אלא זנבו *ve-lo
kishkesh ela zenavo*, or it only moved its tail, right, it only
like flicked its tail, הרי זו פירכוס *harei zu pirchus*, that suffices
by birds. Any movement is okay by birds. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, מאי קמשמע לן *Mai kamashma lan*? So Rava says, oh, we
rule like this תוספתא *Tosefta*. What's the חידוש *chiddush*? All of this
is implicit in the משנה *Mishnah*. כולם תנינא היא *Kulam tanina hi*,
it's all implicit in the משנה *Mishnah*. Why? What did the משנה
*Mishnah* say? משנה *Mishnah* said בהמה דקה *behemah dakah*, a small animal
שפשטה ידה ולא החזירה *she-pashtah yadah ve-lo hichzirah*, that stuck out its
hand without pulling it back, its back, פסולה *pesulah*, is invalid שאין
אלא הוצאת נפש *she-ein ela hotza'at nefesh*, that that's only the expelling
of the soul. So there from that משנה *Mishnah* I could have
inferred every single thing that the תוספתא *Tosefta* spelled out because it
only excluded one case: a בהמה דקה *behemah dakah*, front arm, sticking
it out.
So I could have inferred that that
was clearly—I know—so I could have inferred anything that doesn't have all
of those criteria is okay. I would have inferred יד אין רגל
לא *yad ein regel lo*, it's only a problem when it's just
the hand, if it's the hind leg it's not a problem. דקה
אין גסה לא *dakah ein gasah lo*, it's only a problem by
a small animal, if it's a cow it's not a problem. And
therefore I could have inferred everything in the תוספתא *Tosefta*. So who
needed Rava to quote me the תוספתא *Tosefta*?
Well, it doesn't mention anything about birds.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, עוף איצטריכא ליה דלא תנן *Of itztaricha
lei d'lo tnan*. No, he had to quote the תוספתא *Tosefta* besides
that it was clearer, it also mentioned the case of birds and
that we wouldn't know how to assess birds and the תוספתא *Tosefta*
is clear about that. Okay, so with that we are done with
מסוכנת *mesukenet* and now we go back
to a more, sort of I would say conceptual, less physical discussion
in terms of שחיטה *shechitah* and talking about the שחיטה *shechitah* of
a non-Jew.
Where was this from the beginning?
We did—I don't know, good question.
For a non-Jew or—I'm
sorry, שחיטה *shechitah* for a non-Jew, you're correct. No, actually you're correct.
No, but שחיטה *shechitah* of a non-Jew we did put in the
beginning in the very first פרק *perek* in the list of people
that can שחט *shecht*. Here it's a question of for a non-Jew.
So let's take a look. Even so, it's a little funny it
comes here after all of the much more, you know, physical types
of discussion. So let's take a look at the next משנה *Mishnah*.
השוחט לעובד כוכבים *Ha-shochet l'oved kochavim*, you're שחיטה *shechting* for a non-Jew,
שחיטתו כשירה *shechitato kesherah*, it's valid. Now why not? Okay, and then
you decided you changed your mind and you decided that you wanted
to eat it, or you know, even he owned the cow and
he gave you the cow to שחט *shecht* for him, and then
he offers you some of the meat. Oh, you did such a
nice job שחיטה *shechting*, here take a few pounds home for your
family. Okay, so the שחיטה *shechitah*'s כשר *kosher*. רבי אליעזר פוסל *Rabbi
Eliezer posel*, but רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says it's invalid. I'm sure
you can see why. So אמר רבי אליעזר *Amar Rabbi Eliezer*,
so here's a very nice משנה *Mishnah*, the reasons—a whole back and
forth is spelled out. אמר רבי אליעזר *Amar Rabbi Eliezer*, אפילו שחטה
לאכול לעובד כוכבים מחצר כבד שלה *afilu shechatah le'echol l'oved kochavim mechatzar
kaved shelah*, even if you שחט *shechted* it to feed from the
to the non-Jew from its liver or the lobe of its liver,
פסולה *pesulah*, it's invalid. Why should that make it more כשר *kosher*?
Let's see what his problem is and then we'll go back. שסתם
מחשבת עובד כוכבים oved kochavim. לעבודת כוכבים *She-stam machashevet oved kochavim l'avodat
kochavim*, the normal thinking of a גוי goy. *goy* is for idolatry.
Meaning, okay, so he is assuming that if you're שחיטה *shechting* it
for him—now the question is what does for him mean? Does it
mean it's his cow or does it just mean that you're planning
on giving it to him afterwards? Let's assume that it's his cow,
that at least makes more sense. If it's his cow, he gave
it to you, you're the שוחט *shochet*. So what is he thinking?
He owns the cow, maybe that matters. If he is thinking, "Oh
great, the Jew is שחיטה *shechting* it for me, I'm going now
to offer this in my temple," okay, so if he's thinking about
this as a—as an
idolatrous process or it's the beginning of an offering to give it
to his god, then therefore it makes it a שחיטת עבודה זרה
avoda zara *shechitat avodah zarah* and something שחט *shechted* לעבודה זרה *l'avodah
zarah* is, you know, is an offering to—to an idol and therefore
is forbidden in benefit. Now the obviously—the חידוש *chiddush* here is that
who the heck cares what he's thinking, I'm the one doing the
שחיטה *shechitah*. So רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is saying yes, actually, the
owners can define what the context is and what the meaning is
of the שחיטה *shechitah* even though they're not the ones doing it.
And that's one assumption, and the second assumption is, and I'm going
to not only assume that the owners can define and not just
the person doing it, but I'm going to assume that a normal
non-Jew is—I'm going to have to assume be concerned that a normal
non-Jew when it comes to שחיטה *shechitah* is thinking about using—doing some
type of a gift as an—as an idolatrous gift. Now why does—that
also explains the emphasis of even if he wants to eat one
of the organs, because maybe the standard things that are offered, right,
does it really mean that anytime he שחט *shechts* he's not going
to take it home and have a barbecue? No, maybe it means
of course he's going to have a barbecue after he gives the
fat and the inner organs on the altar. Okay, that would be
a normal thing you would put on the altar, the fat and
the organs, right, and then you take the meat and you eat
the meat. So there it says even if you know that the
non-Jew wants to eat from the liver, apparently that was for some
health purposes, so you might say, "Oh look, he's going to have
an organ, so clearly he's not giving it as a sacrifice," because
maybe the sacrifice was all of the organs. No, that doesn't help
you, you have to still be concerned that he's still planning on
doing some type of an offering with it and therefore it's all
considered a שחיטה לעבודה זרה and invalid. Okay, yes.
What would it make a difference because you know I'm going to
eat the whole thing, then can you trust him or would you
say?
Yeah, I don't know if you can trust him, probably not, probably
would be in the same category of he's going to eat the,
you know, the liver or something, I don't know. Not so simple.
Yeah. And then the name is עובד כוכבים.
Well, and
the original text probably said גוי. We'll have to look at the
original text.
Yes. So, and we're certain that this is a case where it's
his animal, as opposed to your animal and you just want to
like feed him because you
know he's going to eat. We're not certain, but at least let's
deal with that case as an easier case.
Because according to that then it would be kind of hard to,
you know, what do you do with אברהם, Avraham, right? Because he
thought they were עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. Right, right, right.
No, yeah, presumably, presumably it's their animal. Let's take a look. Okay,
so now the גמרא says, אמר רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yosi, so
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, קל וחומר דברים, kal v'chomer devarim, I
can give you a קל וחומר kal v'chomer? that this is not
a problem. What's the קל וחומר? ומה במקום שמחשבה פוסלת, u'ma bimkom
she'machshava poselet, where in a category where thoughts normally are a problem.
When are thoughts do we know a big problem? במוקדשין, bimukdashin, by
קורבנות, korbanos, like by קורבנות korbanos wrong thoughts invalidate all the time.
And nevertheless אין המחשבה הולכת אלא אחר העובד, ein hamachshava holechet ela
achar ha'oved, the only person's thoughts matter are the one doing the
act, the כהן, kohen, the thoughts of the owner are completely irrelevant
as we learned in זבחים. Zevachim.
And if that's true by there, where thoughts really matter, במקום שאין
מחשבה פוסלת, bimkom she'ein machshava poselet, where thoughts don't matter so much,
like by non-קורבנות. korbanos. Okay, thoughts for עבודה זרה avoda zara. matters,
but pretty much any other thoughts don't matter. בחולין, be'chullin, when it's
not a קורבן, korban, אינו דין שלא תהא מחשבה הולכת אלא אחר
השוחט? eino din she'lo tehei machshava holechet ela achar hashochet? Is it
of a- how much more so should it only be what the
actual person doing the שחיטה is thinking and completely irrelevant what somebody
else is thinking, even the owner. So that's a pretty good response.
So let's take a look. Now remember רבי אליעזר assumes two things.
The thought of the owner matters, which is what here is being-
though you know- that רבי, whoever it- רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is
specifically rejecting. And that we assume that a non-Jew is thinking for
עבודה זרה. avoda zara So let's take a look at the גמרא
as it analyzes it. So the גמרא says, הני תנאי אית להו
דרבי אליעזר ברבי יוסי. hani tannai it lehu d'Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Yosi.
The following תנאים, tannaim, meaning the first two תנאים, tannaim, the תנא
קמא tanna kamma who doesn't care and רבי אליעזר who does care
that it was for a non-Jew, both agree with רבי אליעזר ברבי
יוסי. Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Yosi. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
braita. אמר רבי אליעזר ברבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Yosi, רבי
אליעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Yosi says, שמעתי שהבעלים מפגלים. shamati
she'habealim mefaglim.
I actually heard that when it comes to קורבנות, korbanos, not only
can the כהן kohen create פיגול, pigul, but even the owners can
create פיגול. pigul. So the thoughts of the owners do matter. And
if they matter by קדשים, kodashim, then presumably they matter by חולין
chullin as well. Why? Well, we're going to say that now for
the sake of argument. What we're trying to do is spell out
that you could disagree with רבי אליעזר for either by fundamentally disagreeing
that the thoughts of somebody else matters, or by disagreeing with what
we assume the non-Jew is thinking. So the גמרא says like this.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi in the end argued on the principle of
whether somebody else's thoughts matter. Presumably the rabbis earlier in the משנה
who also disagreed didn't argue on that principle. Presumably they argued on
the other principle. Presumably they accepted the thoughts of somebody else matter
and they argued on the principle of what the non-Jew was thinking.
So that's what we're saying right now. We can take- we can
say that both רבי אליעזר and the תנא קמא tanna kamma agree
that the thoughts of somebody else matter by קורבנות korbanos and therefore
also by non-קורבנות. korbanos. מיהו, mihu, here's the debate. תנא קמא סבר,
tanna kamma savar, the תנא קמא tanna kamma would have said, אי
שמעינא דחשיב אין, ei shamina de'chashiv in, if we hear the non-Jew
is saying great I'm going to now give the- you know this
to- you know in my temple, yes, that would be a problem
if we have evidence that that's what he was thinking. אי לאו
לא, ei lav lo, if we don't have evidence we're not going
to assume that's what he was thinking. סתם מחשבת עובד כוכבים לעבודת
כוכבים לא אמרינן. stam machshavat oved kochavim l'avodat kochavim lo amrinan. We
don't say the normal thoughts of a non-Jew are for idolatry. רבי
אליעזר סבר, Rabbi Eliezer savar, רבי אליעזר is of the opinion, אף
על גב דלא שמעינא דחשיב, af al gav d'lo shamina de'chashiv, even
if we didn't hear him say that that's what he was planning,
סתם מחשבת עובד כוכבים לעבודת כוכבים אמרינן. stam machshavat oved kochavim l'avodat
kochavim amrinan. We do say that a non-Jew is thinking about עבודה
זרה avoda zara, especially in the context of slaughtering animals, that he's
going to give something as an offering. Okay, so therefore he's saying
we could say that their debate's not whether the thoughts of another
matter, but what is that other thinking. And then ואתא רבי יוסי
למימר, v'ata Rabbi Yosi l'meimar, comes along רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi to
say, אף על גב דשמעינא דחשיב, af al gav d'shamina de'chashiv, even
if we know the non-Jew is thinking עבודה זרה, avoda zara. זה
מחשב וזה עובד לא אמרינן, ze mechashev v'ze oved lo amrinan, this
one should think and that one should do the act, that we
don't say. We don't care what somebody's doing who's not thinking who's
not doing the act. So the גמרא very nicely said, you know
that רבי אליעזר's position relies on two assumptions: somebody else's thoughts matter
and the other person is thinking עבודה זרה. avodah zarah, So רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi we know explicitly argues on the idea that somebody
else's thoughts matter. Therefore the תנא קמא tanna kamma who presumably has
a different point says may- says maybe I'll grant that, but I
disagree that we can assume what the non-Jew is thinking. Okay, איכא
דאמרי. ika de'amri. He's just going, you know, expanding the תנא קמא.
tanna kamma. All right, so let's take a look. That's one way
of explaining the debate which very nicely has them focusing on two
different part- two different arguments. איכא דאמרי. ika de'amri. איכא דאמרי, Ika
d'amri, איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, he's just going expanding the תנא. Tanna.
All right, so let's take a look. That's one way of explaining
the debate, which very nicely has them focusing on two different part,
two different arguments. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say: בדשמיענא דחשיב פליגי,
bedishmi'ana dechashiv pligi, even when we know the non-Jew is thinking for
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would disagree. But
nevertheless we want him to say something different than רבי יוסי. Rebbi
Yosi. So what would the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say different than
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi if he would say even
if we know the non-Jew is thinking
עבודה זרה avodah zarah it doesn't matter? Here's what we would say.
תנא קמא סבר, Tanna Kamma savar, כי אמרינן זה מחשב וזה עובד,
ki amrinan ze m'chashev v'ze oved, when will I grant you that
somebody else's thoughts matter? הני מילי בפנים, Hanei mili bifnim, I'm willing
to grant it by קרבנות. korbanot. I'm willing to grant that by
a קרבן, korban, you know, maybe it's true, maybe the owner of
the קרבן korban's thoughts can matter. But that's by קרבן. korban. Okay,
אבל בחוץ, aval bachutz, outside of the Temple where normally thoughts are
much less relevant, לא, we would not say that. חוץ מפנים לא
ילפינן. Chutz mipnim lo yafinan. We don't learn out of the Temple
from in the Temple. Top of לט עמוד א. lamed tet amud
aleph. Only in the Temple where thoughts really matter might I say
even the thought of the owner matters. ואתא רבי אלעזר למימר v'ata
Rebbi Elazar l'meimar and רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar says: ילפינן חוץ מפנים.
Yafinan chutz mipnim. No, thoughts outside of the Temple we can learn
from in the Temple, and if they matter in the Temple, the
thoughts of the owner, they'll matter out of the Temple. ואתא רבי
יוסי למימר v'ata Rebbi Yosi l'meimar and comes along רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosi to say אפילו בפנים נמי, afillu bifnim nami, even if it
were in the Temple I wouldn't care if you have a פיגול
piggul thought or an עבודה זרה avodah zarah thought. Why? זה מחשב
וזה עובד לא אמרינן Ze m'chashev v'ze oved lo amrinan that somebody
outside of the one actually doing the act, that somebody else's thoughts
should matter is completely irrelevant. So one approach is, right, that they
all, one approach is is that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
willing to grant that even by חולין chullin the owner's thoughts of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah. could matter, but only when we know about
it. The other approach has them both saying no no no. By
חולין chullin somebody else's thoughts don't matter. I don't care what this
non-Jew is thinking. Okay, and maybe I'll grant the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma might say maybe I'll grant by קרבנות korbanot somebody else's thoughts
could matter, but certainly by non-קרבנות korbanos no. And רבי אלעזר Rebbi
Elazar is saying two things. Number one, not only by קרבנות korbanot
but even by non-קרבנות korbanot the owner's thoughts matter. And number two,
I assume the thoughts of the non-Jew are for עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah, I want to say one point about the issue about somebody
else's thoughts and the difference between קרבנות korbanot and outside and why
other than just are thoughts a bigger deal or not a bigger
deal. And that has to do with just more precise framing about
you know always when we've dealt with in the past issues of
כוונה kavanah and we've dealt with it by שחיטה and by קדשים
kodshim and we dealt with it by the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan and do you require כוונה kavanah and all those questions.
The question always is is that is this a per se requirement
or issue or is it a way of defining the act? Okay,
so let's say you said you require כוונה kavanah by קדשים kodshim
or you require כוונה kavanah by שחיטה which you don't. But let's
say you did. Is it that if you require כוונה kavanah because
one of the criteria is do this act and an addition criteria
is have this thought, have this כוונה, kavanah, or no, to define
it it's just about defining it as the act of שחיטה but
part of what defines or the act of שחיטת קדשים shechitas kodshim
but part of what defines the act is how you are mentally
framing it? But it's about how can we define the act. Why
is that relevant? Because I would say the following: in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash where you have idea like a פיגול piggul thought
invalidates and you have and you need לשמה lishmah and שלא לשמה
shelo lishmah invalidates and all those things, where thoughts play a big
role, it's easier to say that thoughts are a per se problem.
Okay, that a פיגול piggul thought per se invalidates, not just by
redefining the act, but that thought itself is what invalidates. If that's
true, then the thought of anybody related to the קרבן korban can
invalidate, so either the thought of the person doing the עבודה avodah
or the thought of the owner of the קרבן. korban. If thought
invalidates, even if you're not doing any עבודה, avodah, if it's your
קרבן korban and you're having that thought during the עבודה, avodah, that
could very well be a relevant thought to invalidate. But by when
we talk about here about שחיטה and thinking about עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah there's not a הלכה halacha that if you think about עבודה
זרה you invalidate the שחיטה, right? There's not idea that the thought
per se invalidates. What's the הלכה? halacha? That an act of worship,
if you bring
if this is being brought as a sacrifice, right, an act of
worship, that invalidates. So that is about defining the act. There it
makes much much more sense to say that even if you're the
owner, the one doing the act is defining what the act is,
not the owner of the animal. Okay, so a way of understanding
the difference between in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and out, we
could rule that even in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash the owner's
thoughts don't matter. But if they do, a difference could be whether
it's about the thought itself or whether it's about defining the act.
Now you could read disagree, you could say look, it's my cow,
what do I care what you're thinking? You're just my שליח, shaliach,
you're my agent. So even when it comes to defining the act,
since it's my cow and you're doing it for me, I get
to define how that process is looked at, not you. So you
could say even in outside and that's רבי אלעזר, Rebbi Elazar, right?
רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar says the thought of the owner matters even
by חולין chullin and even outside of the Temple. But at least
one way of thinking about it is Is it the thought per
se or is it the act? The more it's about defining the
act, the more I will only pay attention to the person actually
doing the act. Okay, to be continued with this tomorrow.